Railway Labor Executives' Association Miscellany 5300
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association Miscellany
1909-1969
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association (RLEA)
5300
1.5 cubic feet
1.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection contains select records of the Railway Labor Executives' Association.
5596505
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, August 08, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, August 08, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The RLEA was founded in 1926 in response to the passage of the Railway Labor Act. Prior to 1926, there had been an informal association between the railroad labor organizations so that the various chief executives of the different unions could work together to form a unified course of action that would benefit all of their members. This group became more formalized immediately after the end of World War I. The U.S. railroads had been nationalized as part of the war effort, and the railroad labor organizations wanted them to remain under federal management, both because of increased productivity and because of better labor relations with the industry. The effort was ultimately unsuccessful, and the railroads returned to private industry; however, the railroad labor organizations had realized the need to have a united front to counter the carriers and industry groups and lobbyists.
On May 18, 1926, the chief executives of the railroad labor organization met in Washington D.C., formalized their association with By-Laws, and elected officers to serve the newly created RLEA. The original purpose, codified in the original preamble, was co-operative action to obtain and develop consistent interpretations and utilization of the Railway Labor Act. The RLEA was comprised of the chief executives of the 21 railroad labor unions, including the president of the Railway Employees' Department of the AFL, and each member got one vote, regardless of the size of their union. The organization was voluntary, so no member organization was bound by its decisions. Over the course of its existence, various member organizations withdrew and then re-affiliated with the RLEA.
From 1926 to 1938, the RLEA did not maintain an office, but the amount of work and its importance led the RLEA to open an office in Washington DC and employ a full-time Executive Secretary-Treasurer to run it. The RLEA did not engage in collective bargaining itself, but rather lobbied on behalf of its member organizations, securing such achievements as the Railroad Retirement Act and limiting unemployment for its members during the Great Depression. The RLEA's various areas of interest, such as retirement, safety, legal matters, were broken down into committees, each of which reported back to the executive board on the steps being taken in those areas.
Post World War II, the RLEA played a central role in the Marshall Plan, working with non-Communist labor organizations in Western Europe to establish labor policy and also assist in the work of rebuilding the European railroads. The RLEA was also a major factor in international labor union federations, and its decision to affiliate with the International Transport Workers' Federation [ITWF] and to encourage the ITWF not to join with the Soviet affiliated World Federation of Trade Unions was seen as a major victory for the west.
The RLEA, like its member organizations, did not allow African-American members. As such, it was only representing the interests of white railroad employees; black railroad employees were forced, for the most part, to work without recognized union protection. The exception to this was the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters [BSCP], who in 1948 began a series of successful legal challenges to the jurisdictions over various classes of work. As BSCP's successes in the courts mounted up, and the RLEA's member unions and the RLEA itself were being sued for discriminatory practices, the RLEA finally capitulated in 1950, and accepted the BSCP as a member organization.
In 1950, the RLEA joined with the AFL, CIO, and International Association of Machinists to form the United Labor Policy Committee. This committee oversaw the labor representatives of the Wage Stabilization Board.
In the latter half of the 20th century, the importance of the RLEA declined alongside the decline in the railroad industry itself. As its member unions either merged into single entities or disaffiliated from the RLEA its influence waned, as did the number of its members. The RLEA attempted to counter this decline with the purchase of a railroad at least three different times in the 1970s and 1980s, though they were ultimately unsuccessful in this venture. Ongoing internal battles between the remaining chief executives of the railroad unions further weakened the RLEA until in 1997 it disbanded, handing over its responsibilities to the newly formed AFL-CIO Transportation Trades Department.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1909-1969
Bulk dates: 1945-1966
This collection consists of miscellaneous records from the Railway Labor Executives' Association. The majority of the records found in this collection deal with the issues faced by railroad labor in the 1950s and 1960s when the major carriers began to merge and to abandon lines. The applications of the carriers to the Interstate Commerce Committee [ICC] are documented in the Finance Docket filings. Also of note are the speeches by various railroad labor chief executives in which they speak out against the mergers because of the effect they would have on the nation's economy and on local communities whose tax bases depended on the railroad industry. This collection also contains drafts of a study commissioned by the RLEA about railroad mergers. Also found are public relations materials from the RLEA addressing the mergers as well as pushing back against accusations of featherbedding by the carriers. Finally, the correspondence files contain bulletins and circulars issued by the RLEA about various cases that effect the employees represented by their member unions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3007: Maurice Neufeld Papers /4055: James O. Morris Office Files /4212: Kheel Center Current Documents Correspondence 5001: American Association for Labor Legislation Records 5001 mf: American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm 5034: Switchmen's Union of North America Records 5034 MB: Switchmen's Union of North America Memorabilia 5034 P: Switchmen's Union of North America Photographs 5060: U.S. Emergency Board No. 145 Records 5084: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Records 5139: UTU Records 5141: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5149: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Records 5182: William J. Doble Papers 5204 mf: Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5300: Railway Labor Executives' Association Miscellany 5347: Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, ICC, and Erie Lackawanna Briefs Regarding the Railroad Merger 5351: International Association of Machinists vs. S. B. Street Records 5405 mf: Switchmen's Union of North America Constitutions on Microfilm 5478: AFL-CIO Railway Employees' Department Records 5478 mf: AFL-CIO Railway Employees' Department Records on Microfilm 5484: Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5484 AV: Railway Labor Executives' Association Audio-Visual Material 5487: Vernon H. Jensen Collection of International Longshoremen's Association's and Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen's Materials 5488 A: BRAC Chicago Files 5488 B: BRAC Records 5488 C: BRAC Additional Records 5541: Philip Taft Papers 5552: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5583/5: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 5 5622: UTU New York State Legislative Board Selected Files 5663 mf: Collective Bargaining Agreements on Microfilm 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5735: BRAC Additional Records 5833: James A. Paddock Additional Papers 5976 mf: Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Records on Microfilm 5989 mf: Blacks in the Railroad Industry on Microfilm 6030: Archival Collective Bargaining Agreements File 6040 P: Railroad Collection Photographs 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 6047: Archives Information File 6118 AV: Kheel Center AV Collection
Railroads -- United States -- Employees; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Railroads -- Mergers -- United States; Railroads -- Legislation -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States; United States. Railway Labor Act.; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States. Railroad Retirement Board; Keyserling, Leon H. (Leon Hirsch), 1908-1987; Lyon, Arthur E.; Leighty, George E. (George Earle); Beattie, Donald, S.; Harrison, George M. (George McGregor); Kennedy, W. P.; Railway Labor Executives Association
5596505
- Representation Authorization Cards, SUNA, Missouri Pacific Employees, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- RLEA pamphlets: speeches by executive board members, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  W. P. Kennedy, BRT; George M. Harrison, BRC; G. E. Leighty, RLEA Chairman
- "Why railroad men are losing their jobs." Gordon C. Harvey, Switchman, Rock Island Railway, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  circa 1937
- Niagara Frontier Committee for the Defense of America, correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- RLEA Description and General Explanation of S. 1911 and HR 4805, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Amendments to Railroad Retirement Act
- Mergers, general: Press Releases, Correspondence, 1950-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Interurban Electric Railway, abandonment, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  ICC Finance Docket No. 12792
- Merger: Missouri-Pacific Railroad and Chicago and Eastern Illinois Railroad, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  ICC Finance Docket No. 21755
- Merger: Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
  ICC Finance Docket No. 21160
- Rutland Railway, abandonment, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9b)
  ICC Finance Docket No. 21870
- Merger: Seaboard Air Line Railroad and Atlantic Coastline Railroad [folder1 of 2], 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10a)
  ICC Finance Docket No. 21215
- Merger: Seaboard Air Line Railroad and Atlantic Coastline Railroad [folder2 of 2], 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10b)
  ICC finance Docket No. 21215
- RLEA Voting Record: How did your U.S. Senators and Congressmen vote?, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Featherbedding: press releases, correspondence, 1945-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Merger: Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul and Pacific Railroad and Chicago and North Western Railway, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Dispute re assignment of conductors in Escanaba Yards, Michigan
- "Railroad Merger Mania: Its Causes and Cure" [folder 1 of 2], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3a)
  A background manual concerning railroad consolidation and the public interest, from the Railroad Labor Executives' Board.
- "Railroad Merger Mania: Its Causes and Cure" [folder 1 of 2], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3b)
- RLEA, Reports, 1932-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Minneapolis and St. Louis Railroad, potential merger and abandonment, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  ICC Finance Docket No. 10947
- Brief filed by RLEA in front of ICC, in re Oklahoma Railway Co., 1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Railway Labor Act Docket No. 15
- Correspondence, 1936-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- ICC Finance Docket No.s 22102 through 22198 [folder 1 of 4], 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4a)
- ICC Finance Docket No.s 22102 through 22198 [folder 2 of 4], 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4b)
- ICC Finance Docket No.s 22102 through 22198 [folder 3 of 4], 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4c)
- ICC Finance Docket No.s 22102 through 22198 [folder 4 of 4], 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4d)
- Letter from the American Railroad Employees and Investors Association, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous Agreements, 1945 and 1967, 1945-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)